Finding Aid for Arthur W. Burks Papers 1930-1986
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Arthur W. Burks papers 1930-1986, 1950-1984
Burks, Arthur W. (Arthur Walter), 1915-
4.5 linear feet
Professor of philosophy and of computer and communication sciences at the University of Michigan; include papers, appointment books, and topical files relating to his professional interests; also photographs.
90185 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was donated in May 1990 by Arthur W. Burks (Donor No. 7063 ).
The collection is open for research.
Arthur W. Burks, well known as one of the principal designers and a joint inventor of the Electronic Numerical Integrator and Computer (ENIAC) in the 1940s, was born on October 13, 1915, in Duluth, Minnesota. He received his B.A. in mathematics from DePauw University in 1936, and his M.A. and Ph.D. in 1937 and 1941, both in philosophy from the University of Michigan. Throughout his career, Professor Burks pursued both philosophy and computer science, finding many parallels between the two fields.
After earning his Ph.D., Burks found that academic positions in philosophy were scarce at the time, so he took a government course in electrical engineering at the Moore School of Electrical Engineering at the University of Pennsylvania. He soon became an instructor and research engineer at the Moore School, where from June 1943 to February 1946 he worked with John Maunchly and J. Presper Eckert on the research, development, design, and construction of the ENIAC, the first large-scale general-purpose electronic digital computer. His primary responsibility was the ENIAC's multiplier. The ENIAC's original purpose was to speed up the calculations needed to create firing tables, which showed gunners how to aim their weapons. At the time these calculations were done by hand, by mathematicians who were known as "computers" (in fact, Burks' wife, Alice, whom he married in 1943, was one of these mathematicians at the Moore School). Since ENIAC was not completed until 1946, it was not able to contribute much to the war effort, but it did usher in a new era in computation.
After World War II, Burks maintained his dual interest in philosophy and computers. While still at the Moore School, he worked part-time as an instructor of philosophy at Swarthmore College during 1945 and 1946. He spent some time in early 1946 (as well as the summers of 1947 and 1948) at the Institute for Advanced Study at Princeton, where he worked with John von Neumann and Herman Goldstine on developing the logical design of an electronic digital computer. The basic design they produced became the prototype for many computers built by universities, government research units and IBM.
Burks joined the Department of Philosophy at the University of Michigan in 1946 as an assistant professor, becoming associate professor in 1948 and professor in 1954. In 1956 he organized and became the director of the Logic of Computers Group at the University of Michigan. This group was supported by government contracts and conducted research in automata theory, adaptive systems, the interactive use of digital computers, and the simulation of natural systems. In 1957 Burks and a colleague started a graduate program in Computer and Communication Sciences at Michigan, which became a department in the College of Literature, Science, and Arts in 1967. Burks served as the department's chairman from 1967 to 1971. In 1970 Burks received the University of Michigan Distinguished Faculty Achievement Award, and in 1978 he was named the Henry Russel Lecturer, the highest honor the university can bestow upon a senior faculty member.
Professor Burks' career also included a variety of consulting and visiting professor assignments. He served as a consultant with the Burroughs Corporation (1949-1954), directing a research group which worked on the logical design of digital computers for data processing, on user-oriented programming languages and programs to translate them into machine language, and on automata theory. He also served as a consultant to the Argonne National Laboratory (1950-1951), helping to design the ORACLE computer. From July 1965 to December 1966, Burks was a visiting professor at the Indian Institute of Technology in Kanpur, India, and during the 1971-72 school year he held a fellowship at the Center for Advanced Study in the Behavioral Sciences at Stanford.
Professor Burks was particularly interested in Charles Sanders Peirce, founder of the philosophical doctrine of pragmatism, and edited two volumes of Peirce's papers while a research associate in philosophy at Harvard University in 1955. In 1960, as a visiting professor in applied mathematics at the University of Illinois, Burks completed and edited John von Neumann's papers on self-reproducing cellular automata. Professor Burks served as president of the American Philosophical Association (1972-1973) and of the Philosophy of Science Association (1975-1977). He also published numerous articles on the subjects of computers and philosophy, as well as a book Chance, Cause, Reason, in 1977. He and his wife, Alice R. Burks, published two definitive works in the history of computing: a long article, "The ENIAC: First General-Purpose Electronic Computer," in 1981, and a book, The First Electronic Computer: The Atanasoff Story, in 1988 (The University of Michigan Press).
The collection is substantially composed of two series, Papers, 1930-1984 and Topical Files, 1950-1986. Biographical materials and one folder of photographs have been placed at the beginning of the collection.
Subjects:
Burks, Arthur W. (Arthur Walter), 1915-2008.; Computers.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Computer and Communication Sciences.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Philosophy.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Burks, Arthur W. (Arthur Walter), 1915-2008.; Computers.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Biographical materials
  - Vitas, clippings, etc (Box 1)
- Photographs 1932-1983
  The Photographs series consists of one folder of portraits and photographs of Burks at various meetings.
  - Portraits of Arthur Burks and group photos. (Box 1)
- Papers 1930-1984
  The Papers series is arranged chronologically, and consists primarily of correspondence with colleagues and others, but also include other materials, such as articles, awards and speeches. Unfortunately, few materials dated prior to 1950 are included, therefore there is no material dealing with Burks' work on the ENIAC. Misfiling (items filed in the wrong year) has been corrected when possible. Burks' appointment books for the years 1950 to 1977 are located at the end of this series.
  - 1930-1938 (Box 1)
  - 1939-1950 (Box 1)
  - 1951-1952 (Box 1)
  - 1953 (Box 1)
  - 1954 (Box 1)
  - 1955 (Box 1)
  - 1956 (Box 1)
  - 1957 (Box 1)
  - 1958 (Box 1)
  - 1959 (Box 1)
  - 1960, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - 1961, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - 1962, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - 1963 (Box 1)
  - 1964 (Box 1)
  - 1965, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - 1966 (Box 1)
  - 1967, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - 1968, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - 1969, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - 1970, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - 1971, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - 1972, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - 1973, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - 1974, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - 1975, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - 1976, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - 1977, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - 1978, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - 1979, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - 1980
    - folder 1 (Box 2)
    - folder 2 (Box 3)
  - 1981, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - 1982, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - 1983, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - 1984, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Appointment books
    - 1950-1955 (Box 3)
    - 1956-1962 (Box 3)
    - 1963-1968 (Box 3)
    - 1969-1973 (Box 3)
    - 1974-1977 (Box 3)
- Topical Files 1950-1986
  The Topical Files are arranged alphabetically. The researcher should note that there is considerable overlap between the two series. The Topical Files include some correspondence, and the Papers include some material on topics covered in the topical files. The two types of files reflect Burks' original filing system. Of interest in this series are files detailing Burks' research activities, and several files relating to the Department of Computer and Communication Sciences at Michigan.
  - Arisbe (Charles Peirce's home) 1974-1977 (Box 3)
  - Articles and speeches 1973-1982 (Box 3)
  - Atomic Energy Commission Computer Advisory Group 1960-1962 (Box 3)
  - Computer Science Pioneer Award 1982-1986 (Box 3)
  - Cause, Chance and Reason grants
    - National Science Foundation 1962-1972 (Box 3)
    - University of Michigan, Rackham School of Graduate Studies 1962-1977 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence
    - Foreign 1967-1976 (Box 3)
    - Lugg, Wang and Uchii 1973-1976 (Box 4)
    - H. Nishio 1974-1975 (Box 4)
    - Nancy Stern 1977-1979 (Box 4)
    - S. Ulam 1971 (Box 4)
  - Digitronics v. the New York Racing Association 1974 (Box 4)
  - ENIAC patent agreements 1964-1965 (Box 4)
  - Fellowship applications 1971 (Box 4)
  - Festschrift for Frankena, Stevenson & Brandt 1978 (Box 4)
  - Freedom and Automata 1977 (Box 4)
  - Gobel letter re: von Neumann, notes 1961-1964 (Box 4)
  - Honeywell v. Sperry Rand (ENIAC case) 1972 (Box 4)
  - India 1966-1968 (Box 4)
  - Indian Institute of Technology 1967-1972 (Box 4)
  - Journal of Computer and System Sciences 1981-1986 (Box 4)
  - Kanpur Indo-American Program Advisory Committee 1967-1968 (Box 4)
  - National Science Foundation
    - History and Philosophy of Science Subcommittee 1978-1979 (Box 4)
    - Modal Logic Support 1979 (Box 4)
  - Peirce editing 1973-1974 (Box 4)
  - Philosophy of Science Association
    - Critical Research Problems Conference 1978 (Box 4)
    - General 1975-1976 (Box 4)
  - Philosophy of Science journal 1972-1975 (Box 4)
  - Polish Logic Machine and Burroughs 5000, 1962 (Box 4)
  - Research interests 1975-1980 (Box 4)
  - Research plans 1983-1986 (Box 4)
  - Russel lecture 1978 (Box 4)
  - Sabbaticals/fellowships 1953-1954, 1962-1963 (Box 4)
  - Sabbatical 1978-1979 (Box 4)
  - Statements of accomplishments 1975-1983 (Box 4)
  - Synthese and other journals 1965-1979 (Box 4)
  - Tanner lecture introduction 1980 (Box 4)
  - University of Chicago Press
    - 1968-1974 (Box 4)
    - publicity 1974-1980 (Box 4)
  - University of Illinois Press 1982-1983 (Box 4)
  - University of Michigan
    - Computer and Communication Sciences Department
      - 1980 (Box 4)
      - Evaluation 1975-1976 (Box 4)
      - Executive Committee
        - 1979 (Box 4)
        - 1981-1982 (Box 5)
        - 1982-1983 (Box 5)
      - External review committee visit 1980 (Box 5)
      - History (Box 5)
      - Merger with Computer, Information and Control Engineering (CICE) 1983 (Box 5)
      - Merger with Electrical Engineering Dept. 1986 (Box 5)
      - Review 1973 (Box 5)
      - Self-Evaluation, Supplement 1979 (Box 5)
    - Computer Ethics Subcommittee 1979 (Box 5)
    - Electrical Engineering and Computer Science Dept., Bylaws 1984 (Box 5)
    - Logic of Computers Group 1962-1978 (Box 5)
    - Niemeyer tenure case 1974-1975 (Box 5)
    - Philosophy Department
      - 1978-1984 (Box 5)
      - History (Box 5)
    - University of Michigan Press 1959-1971 (Box 5)
Related Material
A related collection held by the Bentley Library is the University of Michigan Logic of Computers Group records.